<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>口译资料 on Byte Prince</title>
    <link>https://byteprince.com/tags/%E5%8F%A3%E8%AF%91%E8%B5%84%E6%96%99/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 口译资料 on Byte Prince</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 13:25:30 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://byteprince.com/tags/%E5%8F%A3%E8%AF%91%E8%B5%84%E6%96%99/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>江泽民同志关于西藏问题同克林顿总统的讲话</title>
      <link>https://byteprince.com/posts/69a6621d/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 13:25:30 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://byteprince.com/posts/69a6621d/</guid>
      <description>英语口译学习资料</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[

<p><strong>西藏自古以来是中华人民共和国不可分割的领土。</strong></p>

<p>全文整理如下：</p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>我想，很抱歉，还要耽误你们5分钟。</p>

<p><strong>翻译：</strong>I&rsquo;m sorry, I have to take up your additional five minutes.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>我想讲讲关于达赖喇嘛的问题。</p>

<p><strong>翻译：</strong>So, I&rsquo;d like to say a few words on the Dalai Lama.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>克林顿总统他也很关心达赖喇嘛，应该说，我们的西藏从达赖喇嘛59年走了以后，整个的西藏发生了翻天覆地的变化。</p>

<p><strong>翻译：</strong>President Clinton is also interested in this question, in Dalai Lama.Actually, since the Dalai Lama left in 1959,earthshaking changes have taken place in Tibet.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>第一，政教合一的制度从此一去不复返了,</p>

<p><strong>翻译：</strong>First, the system of theocracy has forever become bygones,</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>虽然很遗憾的，它比欧洲的 Renaissance, 这个文艺复兴之前那个政教合一，就是分开的时间要比它那个晚的多。</p>

<p><strong>翻译：</strong>but though it is unfortunate that the disappearance of this the ocracy was much later than the demise of the ocracy in Europe, before the Renaissance.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>另外一个，在达赖政权下面的一百多（万）的农奴，解放了。我曾经90年到这个解放的农奴家里头做过客。</p>

<p><strong>翻译：</strong>And more than 1 million serfs under the rule of the Dalai Lama were liberated. In 1990, when I was inTibet, I went to visit the liberated serfs.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>那么西藏现在实行了民族自治，有自己的人民的自己的政府。</p>

<p><strong>翻译：</strong>And now the system of national autonomy is in practice in Tibet, And the people there, they have their Tibetan autonomous region government.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>在我到中央工作以后，我动员了我们29个省市，支持西藏，包括一些生产比较落后的，比如青海省，也要拿出钱来。大概将近80亿人民币，62个建设项目，现在建成了。</p>

<p><strong>翻译：</strong>Since I came to work in the central government, I have urged the rest 29 provinces municipalities and autonomous regions to assist Tibet in its development, even including those provinces that are not very developed, such as Qinghai province. So altogether,nearly 8 billion RMB yuan of financial resources were raised, and already 62 projects have been completed in Tibet.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>另外，我们对西藏的宗教信仰自由，宪法有保护。对于许多的庵观寺院，包括那个拉萨有名的布达拉宫，我们花了将近一亿人民币，一吨重的金子，把它焕然一新。</p>

<p><strong>翻译：</strong>As for the freedom of religious belief，there is clear stipulations in our constitution for the protection of the religious belief, and this also including in Tibet.And we have also spent a lot of money in renovating the lamaseries and the temples in Tibet and we have spent 100 million RMB yuan and one ton of gold in renovating the Potala Palace.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>我想，对于这个西藏来讲，达赖喇嘛，刚才克林顿总统提到的，如果说他承认，“西藏是中国不可分割的一部分”，同时呢，他必须要承认，“台湾是中国的一个省”，那么，我看我们谈判的大门是敞开着的，而且我们有若干的沟通的渠道。这一点呢，我希望，达赖他能够有积极的变化。</p>

<p><strong>翻译：</strong>Just now, President Clinton also mentioned the Tibetan issue and dialogue with the Dalai Lama, Actually, as long as the Dalai Lama can publicly make a statement and a commitment that Tibet is an inalienable part of China and he must also recognizes Taiwan as a province of China, then the door to dialogue and negotiation is open.Actually, we having serveral channels of communications with the Dalai Lama. So I hope the Dalai Lama will make positive response in this regard.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>最后，我还要讲一句，中国的宪法对于西藏的宗教自由，包括别的，中国其他各地的，其他的宗教的自由，是保护的。但是我本人，作为中华人民共和国的国家主席来讲，我是共产党人士，无神论者，但是丝毫不影响，对于西藏的宗教自由的尊重。但是呢，我还是有一个问题，就是我去年访美的时候，也包括到欧洲的一些国家，我发现许多人，现代的文明，也是教育木平都很高，科学技术科学技术水平都很高，但是他们呢，好像还很信，这个，就是刺嘛教的教义。就这一点呢，我也正在带着一个问题，在研究，why，为什么？</p>

<p><strong>翻译：</strong>Finally, I want to emphasize that according to Chinese constitution, the freedom of religious belief in Tibet, and also in throughout China, is protected.But as the President of the People&rsquo;s Republic of China, and as a member of the Communist Party, I self am an atheist.But this will by no means affect my respect for the religious freedom in Tibet. But still , Ihave a question. That is, during my visit to the United States last year and also during my previous visit to other European countries, I found that although the education and the science and the technology have developed to a very high level and the people are now ejoying modern civilization, still quite a number of them have a belief in Lamaism. So this is a question that I&rsquo;m still studying and looking into. I want to find out the reason why.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>我感觉克林顿总统，他是非常坚持美国利益的。我呢，也坚持中国的利益。但是我跟他两人，还是可以非常友好的交谈协商。这是什么？This is democracy.</p>

<p><strong>翻译：</strong>I think President Clinton is a strong defender of the American inerests and I am a strong defender of the Chinese interest. But despite that, we still can have very friendly exchanges of views and discussion.And I think that is democracy.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>我想说明，我们有很多值得相互学习的地方。</p>

<p><strong>翻译：</strong>And I want to stress that actually there are a lot of areas in which we can learn from each other.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>江：</strong>If you agree, I think, we will finish this.（台下笑）</p>

<p><strong>Clinton:</strong> I agree&hellip;</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="参考资料">参考资料</h3>

<p>视频来源：<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ErgLIoWzd4s&amp;ab_channel=%E9%95%BF%E8%80%85%E6%B1%9F%E6%B3%BD%E6%B0%91%E7%B2%89%E4%B8%9D%E4%BF%B1%E4%B9%90%E9%83%A8%E3%80%90YouTube%E9%95%B7%E8%80%85%E6%9C%80%E5%85%A8%E8%A7%86%E9%A2%91%E5%BA%AB-%E5%AE%98%E6%96%B9%E8%9B%A4%E7%B5%B2%E5%AE%B6%E5%9C%92%E3%80%91%5BOfficial%5D">Youtube</a></p>

<p>本内容基于该视频整理，仅供<strong>英语口译学习</strong>使用，请勿用于非法用途。</p>

<p>转载请注明出处: <a href="https://byteprince.com">https://byteprince.com</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
